<idea-plugin allow-bundled-update="true">
  <id>org.jetbrains.debugger.streams</id>
  <name>Java Stream Debugger</name>
  <vendor>JetBrains</vendor>
  <category>JVM Tools</category>
  <dependencies>
    <plugin id="com.intellij.java"/>
    <module name="intellij.debugger.streams.core"/>
  </dependencies>

  <description><![CDATA[
      <p>Visualizes chains of operations on Java streams.</p>
      <p>In some ways, Stream API is better than traditional loop approach: it takes full advantage of modern multi-core architectures,
      and lets you process data in a declarative way. What's also good is that this approach helps to avoid the state issues, and the
      code written in it looks more elegant. But, there's a certain downside to it: the code sometimes is sure hard to read, understand,
      and, of course, to debug.</p>
      <p>This plugin is here to amend that and offer solutions to the issues you might run into. It extends the <em>Debugger</em>
      tool window by adding the <em>Trace Current Stream Chain</em> button, which becomes active when debugger stops inside of a
      chain of Stream API calls.</p>

      <img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bibaev/static/master/debugger-stop.png" height="300" width="750">

      <p>After you click it, the current data stream is evaluated and you get a visualization of what exactly happens to each element
      from the first call to last, with changes occurring gradually as it's passing thru all the steps:</p>

      <img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bibaev/static/master/flat_mode.png" height="300" width="750">

      <p>The <em>Split Mode button</em> in the left bottom corner lets you choose whether you want to see all operations at once or
      separately:</p>

      <img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bibaev/static/master/split_mode.png" height="300" width="750">

      <p>In the latter mode, you can switch between operations manually using the tabs on top.</p>
    ]]></description>

  <extensions defaultExtensionNs="org.jetbrains.platform.debugger.streams">
    <librarySupport implementation="com.intellij.debugger.streams.lib.impl.StandardLibrarySupportProvider"/>
    <librarySupport implementation="com.intellij.debugger.streams.lib.impl.StreamExLibrarySupportProvider"/>
    <librarySupport implementation="com.intellij.debugger.streams.lib.impl.JBIterableSupportProvider"/>
  </extensions>
</idea-plugin>
